Guide to the Student Peace Union Records TAM.057
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Student Peace Union Records
1959-1964
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Student Peace Union (U.S.)
Vickers, George
TAM.057
0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box.
The Student Peace Union (1959-1964) was an intercollegiate group organized by socialist, pacifist and other anti-war students that was critical of the foreign policy of both the U.S. and the Soviet Union, and protested against the arms race, nuclear weapons testing, racial segregation, the U.S. position during the Cuban Missile Crisis (October, 1962), and the U.S. involvement in Vietnam. The collection contains correspondence, minutes, reports and bulletins documenting activism and SPU annual conventions.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Photocopied collection of records pertaining to the Student Peace Union, an intercollegiate student group organized in 1959 "to study the causes of war and seek constructive alternatives," and "to coordinate the work for peace among students and young people." Later (1960) merged with College Peace Union. The founders and leaders of the SPU were associated with the Young Peoples Socialist League and pacifists associated with the Fellowship of Reconciliation and the American Friends Service Committee. The SPU took a "Third Camp" position, criticizing the foreign policies of both the United States and the Soviet Union. SPU membership peaked in 1962 at 3500, but declined with the rise of the New Left and Students for a Democratic Society, and the organization dissolved in 1964.
Sources:
For more information, see the entry in the Encyclopedia of the American Left. See also: Altbach, Philip G., Student Politics in America: a Historical Analysis(1974).
Scope and Content Note
Collection includes correspondence among leadership discussing policy, tactics, and organizational activity. There are also convention reports, minutes of steering committee, and SPU two publications, the Discussion Bulletin and the Student Peace Union Bulletin. Philip G. Altbach was national chairman. Groups in touch with SPU included American Friends Service Committee, War Resisters' League, and Students for a Democratic Society. Situations most actively protested against were: the arms race, nuclear weapons testing, racial segregation, the U.S. position during the Cuban Missile Crisis (October, 1962), and the U.S. involvement in Vietnam.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into 1 series.
Missing Title
Container list
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by George Vickers, 1974. The accession number associated with this gift is 1964.002.
Reports.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States.; Civil rights movements -- United States.; Bulletins.; Student movements -- United States.; Cuban Missile Crisis, 1962.; Nuclear disarmament.; Peace movements -- United States.; Altbach, Philip G.; College Peace Union; American Friends Service Committee; War Resisters League; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Young People's Socialist League; Student Peace Union Bulletin; Vickers, George
- Container list
  - Correspondence, Internal Documents, Minutes, Publications, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Council, Constitution, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Internal Documents, Minutes, Publications, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National Council, Convention, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Internal Documents, Minutes, Publications, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Council, Convention, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Internal Documents, Minutes, Publications, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Council, Convention, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, Internal Documents, Minutes, Publications, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Council, Convention, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)